<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-05-04T09:23:11-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bethlehem and Ben’s amazing blog</title><subtitle>This site will be used for our final project, a blog about healthcare analytics. The main topic will be focusing on the trend of consumption of resources in relation to the supplies or resources available in the healthcare system.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hypothesis Testing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/01/hypothesis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hypothesis Testing" /><published>2022-05-01T13:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-01T13:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/01/hypothesis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/01/hypothesis.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/SexDistHistogram.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;graph&quot;&gt;Graph&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above is an overlaid histogram of the male and female prevention rates and a box-and-whisker plot. The purpose of creating the histogram is to see if our data were normally distributed across both sexes, which seems to be the case with a slight skew to the left. The hypothesis we decided to work from was to determine if there are any variances in the preventative measures succeession rates between males and females. Therefore, we selected the student t-test as our measurement tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon inspecting the graph, we notice that the men seemed to have an overall higher success rate in satisfying the CDC’s preventative measures guidelines than the women. This observation ran contrary to Ben’s expectations as he predicted the contrary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We read our data into a Pandas dataframe in our local Python environment and then proceeded to separate the data into male and female dataframe objects. We then calculated the mean values of the preventative measures percentage columns for both the male and female dataframes. Then we aggregated the means by state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before sending the data through scipy.stats’s t-test_ind function, we needed to preprocess the data as the function could not handle numbers with such large precision values. To work around this issue, we passed the data through scipy.special’s logsumexp function, which returns the log sum of the exponent of the input.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/SexDistHistogram.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/SexDistHistogram.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Curation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/30/dataCuration.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Curation" /><published>2022-04-30T09:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-30T09:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/30/dataCuration</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/30/dataCuration.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-curators&quot;&gt;Data Curators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CDC is a U.S. Government entity charged with the responsibility of protecting the citizens of the United States from any illness, virus or disease that poses a threat to our country’s well-being. The members of the CDC often conduct scientific experiments, collect data, host and conduct public-health seminars all in order to make efforts to disseminate information to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;places-motivation&quot;&gt;PLACES Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of PLACES was to provide information on a zip code-by-zip code basis, identify key health problems, develop localized plans moving forward, and differentiate the health threats affecting citizens living in various areas such as urban, rural or suburban areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;potential-bias&quot;&gt;Potential Bias&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We identified a few weaknesses of the dataset where bias may affect ongoing or future analysis predicated on this dataset and datasets curated in a similar fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, this dataset is a survey over the phone to various participants across the country whose responses must all be ‘yes’ to every preventative measure the CDC outlines in its guidelines in order to be counted in the survey. For this reason alone, this may explain why the response rate or signal is relatively low (approximately 35% across all states and regions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, some states such as California and Texas have way more participating locations than other states such as Alaska or North Dakota. While this trend should makes logical sense if the motivation is to study as many people as possible, the consequence or potential source of bias manifests in the lack of representation of less populated areas of the country. Furthermore, there wasn’t a single rural or suburban location or locus of participants in this dataset, which means that no information was gathered for people living in these types of environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-quality&quot;&gt;Data Quality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dataset we selected was nowhere near ready for analysis. The main focus of this dataset is targeting population groups in different geographic areas, but the data for the geolocations were nested inside of a data object in the form of strings. This made geospatial analysis impossible to conduct as is because the software we used (GeoPandas and Shapely) required the data to be in a different format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, most of the metadata on the CDC’s websites hardly explained any of the actual fields of the dataset we worked with. The methodology seemed to explain more about the data rather than the documentation which was rather unsettling if the CDC is determined to inform the public about health matters. Navigating through the dataset was not difficult, rather it took mostly common sense to parse through the meaningless pieces of information to select the meaningful parts. Additionally, having Bethlehem’s expertise in healthcare made understanding the data easier, which made the analysis more straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dataset has no security or privacy protections as this came from the CDC, whose objectives include disseminating health-related information to the American public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, while this dataset being highly available is useful as well as the CDC offering free visualization tools to interact with the data on its website, it has many flaws when it comes to conducting analysis outside of their website. Having the dataset not being prepared in a suitable format for analysis and subsequent extracting, loading and transforming does come with the territory of Data Analytics, it does make one wonder how the CDC manages to achieve their goals of disseminating data with this dataset having so few variables and documentation with little to no explanatory power.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Data Curators The CDC is a U.S. Government entity charged with the responsibility of protecting the citizens of the United States from any illness, virus or disease that poses a threat to our country’s well-being. The members of the CDC often conduct scientific experiments, collect data, host and conduct public-health seminars all in order to make efforts to disseminate information to the public.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/Whiteboard.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/Whiteboard.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Questions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/29/Questions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Questions" /><published>2022-04-29T09:26:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-29T09:26:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/29/Questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/29/Questions.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;questions&quot;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given our dataset, we chose to address differences in participation of the PLACES survey between the two sexes. There were other considerations for our research such as assessing geographical differences of the PLACES survey locations. The problem with that specific idea is the dataset doesn’t seem to include any rural or suburban areas despite one of the goals of the PLACES initative being able to differentiate the health problems across different environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparing the sexes seems to be the least problematic given our dataset as there is an even distribution of men and women. What would be neat to see are differences between the male and female prevention rates to see if there is any causal or behavioral explanation to inspect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Questions Given our dataset, we chose to address differences in participation of the PLACES survey between the two sexes. There were other considerations for our research such as assessing geographical differences of the PLACES survey locations. The problem with that specific idea is the dataset doesn’t seem to include any rural or suburban areas despite one of the goals of the PLACES initative being able to differentiate the health problems across different environments.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/Whiteboard.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/Whiteboard.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Metadata</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/16/metadata.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Metadata" /><published>2022-04-16T10:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-16T10:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/16/metadata</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/16/metadata.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;jupyter-notebook-image&quot;&gt;Jupyter Notebook image&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/metadata.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dataset we selected was rather messy before we started our analysis. For example, for the map projections, using the ‘GeoLocation’ column was not possible unless we decoupled the object and converted the string data into a floating-point data type. Furthermore, the dataset contained many columns or fields of metadata regarding this dataset which was worthless for any analysis (starting with about 30 columns), so we dropped more than half of the original columns. The image above shows our end product of data cleansing using Python with the Pandas library.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Jupyter Notebook image</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/metadata.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/metadata.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cities Count Histogram</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/10/citycounts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cities Count Histogram" /><published>2022-04-10T09:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-10T09:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/10/citycounts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/10/citycounts.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/statecounts.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This histogram shows the counts of unique cities by state the CDC survey was conducted. The bars colored dark purple represent the states that had the most cities participating in the survey. The purpose of this graph is to demonstrate a possible bias of over-representing some cities as opposed to others.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/statecounts.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/statecounts.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PLACES Survey Locations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/09/citiesAnalysis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PLACES Survey Locations" /><published>2022-04-09T09:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-09T09:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/09/citiesAnalysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/09/citiesAnalysis.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/PlacesUSA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This map shows all locations where the PLACES surveys took place. The majority of the survey calls were made in the states of California, Texas, Florida, Illinois, and Michigan. The points colored in red on the map whereas everywhere is marked in blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is notable about this observation in regards to the survey is that the majority of the US population seems to be concentrated in certain environments. If the probability of most chronic illnesses, diseases and viruses affecting the target population can be traced to the environment, then a potential bias surrounding these five states and their environments’ characteristics may be affecting the PLACES survey efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/PlacesUSA.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/PlacesUSA.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>