<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-05-04T15:03:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bethlehem and Ben’s amazing blog</title><subtitle>This site will be used for our final project, a blog about healthcare analytics. The main topic will be focusing on the trend of consumption of resources in relation to the supplies or resources available in the healthcare system.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Our Story</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/03/ourStory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Story" /><published>2022-05-03T10:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-03T10:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/03/ourStory</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/03/ourStory.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;our-story&quot;&gt;Our Story&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/icon.png&quot; style=&quot;width:200px;height:200px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, the world changed indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are no longer living in the same world we used to live in prior to COVID-19. In the current post-pandemic era, Public Health has become a center-piece conversation on news channels, broadcasts, universities, and college campuses. The devastating effects of COVID19 still are felt now 2 years later. As graduate students studying Big Data, we wanted to explore a dataset that was based in the real world to answer this important question: How is real world data interpreted to gain more insight into estimating the impact and limitations of a particular health initiative?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are known COVID-19 infections that are present in 176 countries–making the pandemic the most significant threat to humanity since World War II. Unlike the second world war, the outbreak of the coronavirus crisis had been anticipated by public health researchers. For years infectious disease specialists have been raising the alarm and spreading awareness about an outbreak. What were some of the limitations for their research–and data to be spread to the public?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big part of the limitations that we will touch on our project, is the lack of availability for consistent, clean data that can inform trend lines. We have chosen to explore data directly from CDC (Centers for Disease Control). As part of our graduate work, we will cover data from PLACES (Population Level Analysis Community Estimates), which is a collaboration between CDC, the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, and the CDC Foundation. PLACES provides us with health data for small areas across the country–which in turn, allows local health departments, and jurisdictions (regardless of population size and rurarility) to better understand the burden and geographic distribution of health measures in their respective areas while assisting them with planning public health interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Our Story</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Big Data in Healthcare</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/02/bigdataHealth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Big Data in Healthcare" /><published>2022-05-02T10:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-02T10:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/02/bigdataHealth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/02/bigdataHealth.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/statecounts.png&quot; /&gt;
This is a bar graph showing the prevalence of men and women aged 65 years and older who are up-to-date with the recommended core set of clinical preventive services. This project provides model-based small area estimates for 27 measures of chronic disease related to unhealthy behaviors (5), health outcomes (13), and use of preventive services (9). Data were provided by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), Division of Population Health, Epidemiology and Surveillance Branch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/PlacesUSA.png&quot; /&gt;
This map shows all locations where the PLACES surveys took place. The majority of the survey calls were made in the states of California, Texas, Florida, Illinois, and Michigan. The points colored in red on the map whereas everywhere is marked in blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is notable about this observation in regards to the survey is that the majority of the US population seems to be concentrated in certain environments. If the probability of most chronic illnesses, diseases and viruses affecting the target population can be traced to the environment, then a potential bias surrounding these five states and their environments’ characteristics may be affecting the PLACES survey efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">This is a bar graph showing the prevalence of men and women aged 65 years and older who are up-to-date with the recommended core set of clinical preventive services. This project provides model-based small area estimates for 27 measures of chronic disease related to unhealthy behaviors (5), health outcomes (13), and use of preventive services (9). Data were provided by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), Division of Population Health, Epidemiology and Surveillance Branch.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Curation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/30/dataCuration.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Curation" /><published>2022-04-30T09:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-30T09:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/30/dataCuration</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/30/dataCuration.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-curators&quot;&gt;Data Curators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one of their goals entails disseminating information to the public, members of the CDC often conduct scientific experiments, collect data, host and conduct public-health seminars and place their results and data on their website. This centralization model makes finding specific information, research efforts and general inquiries easy to address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;places-motivation&quot;&gt;PLACES Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of PLACES was to provide information on a zip code-by-zip code basis, identify key health problems, develop localized plans moving forward, and differentiate the health threats affecting citizens living in various areas such as urban, rural or suburban areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-quality&quot;&gt;Data Quality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dataset we selected was nowhere near ready for analysis. The main focus of this dataset is targeting population groups in different geographic areas, but the data for the geolocations were nested inside of a data object in the form of strings. This made geospatial analysis impossible to conduct with our code as the dataset came downloaded, so there was plenty of data cleaning that had to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, most of the metadata on the CDC’s websites hardly explained any of the actual fields of the dataset we worked with. The methodology of the research seemed to explain more about the data rather than the dataset’s own documentation which was rather unsettling if the CDC is determined to inform the public about health matters. However, having Bethlehem’s expertise in healthcare made understanding the data easier, which made the analysis more straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did not encounter any security protocols or identity authentications to acquire this dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Data Curators As one of their goals entails disseminating information to the public, members of the CDC often conduct scientific experiments, collect data, host and conduct public-health seminars and place their results and data on their website. This centralization model makes finding specific information, research efforts and general inquiries easy to address.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Bias</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/30/dataBias.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Bias" /><published>2022-04-30T08:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-30T08:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/30/dataBias</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/30/dataBias.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;potential-bias&quot;&gt;Potential Bias&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/biasimage.jpeg&quot; style=&quot;width=100px;height=220px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identified a few weaknesses of the dataset where bias may affect ongoing or future analysis predicated on this dataset and datasets curated in a similar fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, this dataset is a survey over the phone to various participants across the country whose responses must all be ‘yes’ to every preventative measure the CDC outlines in its guidelines in order to be counted in the survey. For this reason alone, this may explain why the response rate or signal is relatively low (approximately 35% across all states and regions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, some states such as California and Texas have way more participating locations than other states such as Alaska or North Dakota. While this trend should makes logical sense if the motivation is to study as many people as possible, the consequence or potential source of bias manifests in the lack of representation of less populated areas of the country.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Potential Bias</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Questions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/29/Questions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Questions" /><published>2022-04-29T09:26:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-29T09:26:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/29/Questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/29/Questions.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;questions&quot;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given our dataset, we chose to address differences in participation of the PLACES survey between the two sexes. There were other considerations for our research such as assessing geographical differences of the PLACES survey locations. The problem with that specific idea is the dataset doesn’t seem to include any rural or suburban areas despite one of the goals of the PLACES initative being able to differentiate the health problems across different environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparing the sexes seems to be the least problematic given our dataset as there is an even distribution of men and women. What would be neat to see are differences between the male and female prevention rates to see if there is any causal or behavioral explanation to inspect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Questions Given our dataset, we chose to address differences in participation of the PLACES survey between the two sexes. There were other considerations for our research such as assessing geographical differences of the PLACES survey locations. The problem with that specific idea is the dataset doesn’t seem to include any rural or suburban areas despite one of the goals of the PLACES initative being able to differentiate the health problems across different environments.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/Whiteboard.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/Whiteboard.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Technologies Implemented</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/17/technologies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technologies Implemented" /><published>2022-04-17T10:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-17T10:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/17/technologies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/17/technologies.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;hardware-requirements&quot;&gt;Hardware Requirements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We utilized laptops that run both Windows and macOS operating systems. To replicate this analysis, we recommend your machine has at least 16GB of Random Access Memory (RAM).
&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/applelog.jpeg&quot; style=&quot;width:200px;height:200px&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/windowsIcon.png&quot; style=&quot;width:200px;height:200px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;software-requirements&quot;&gt;Software Requirements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our blog site deployment and source control, we used GitHub Pages and GitHub respectively. We built the site using Jekyll.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/jekyll_icon.png&quot; style=&quot;width:650px;height:280px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analysis portion of our blog was done in Python. We utilized the Visual Studio Code IDE as well as its Jupyter Notebook plugin to develop the code. The visualizations were created using the Plotly library and the geospatial visual used Plotly, Shapely, and GeoPandas. The Hypothesis testing was conducted using the Scipy library. Lastly, the data reading and manipulations were mostly handled by the Pandas library, namely the unique dataframe object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/pythonlogo.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Hardware Requirements We utilized laptops that run both Windows and macOS operating systems. To replicate this analysis, we recommend your machine has at least 16GB of Random Access Memory (RAM). Software Requirements For our blog site deployment and source control, we used GitHub Pages and GitHub respectively. We built the site using Jekyll.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Descriptive Analysis</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/16/descriptiveAnalysis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Descriptive Analysis" /><published>2022-04-16T10:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-16T10:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/16/descriptiveAnalysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/16/descriptiveAnalysis.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;jupyter-notebook-image&quot;&gt;Jupyter Notebook image&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/metadata.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dataset we selected was rather messy before we started our analysis. For example, for the map projections, using the ‘GeoLocation’ column was not possible unless we decoupled the object and converted the string data into a floating-point data type. Furthermore, the dataset contained many columns or fields of metadata regarding this dataset which was worthless for any analysis (starting with about 30 columns), so we dropped more than half of the original columns. The image above shows our end product of data cleansing using Python with the Pandas library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/descriptiveStatistics.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above is a picture of the descriptive statistics of the dataset we used for our analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Jupyter Notebook image</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/metadata.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/metadata.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Results and Findings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/08/results.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Results and Findings" /><published>2022-04-08T13:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-08T13:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/08/results</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/08/results.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/SexDistHistogram.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;graph&quot;&gt;Graph&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above is an overlaid histogram of the male and female prevention rates and a box-and-whisker plot. The purpose of creating the histogram is to see if our data were normally distributed across both sexes, which seems to be the case with a slight skew to the left. The hypothesis we decided to work from was to determine if there are any variances in the preventative measures succeession rates between males and females. Therefore, we selected the student t-test as our measurement tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon inspecting the graph, we notice that the men seemed to have an overall higher success rate in satisfying the CDC’s preventative measures guidelines than the women. This observation ran contrary to Ben’s expectations as he predicted the contrary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We read our data into a Pandas dataframe in our local Python environment and then proceeded to separate the data into male and female dataframe objects. We then calculated the mean values of the preventative measures percentage columns for both the male and female dataframes. Then we aggregated the means by state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before sending the data through scipy.stats’s t-test_ind function, we needed to preprocess the data as the function could not handle numbers with such large precision values. To work around this issue, we passed the data through scipy.special’s logsumexp function, which returns the log sum of the exponent of the input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hypothesis-test-results&quot;&gt;Hypothesis Test Results&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/finalResults.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;New Image&quot; style=&quot;width:1000px;height:180px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above is a screenshot of our student t-test. As the p-value &amp;lt; 0.05, we fail to reject the null hypothesis, meaning that the variance in mean between the men and women’s rates of CDC prevention compliance cannot be assumed to be different. In other words, we lack sufficient, data-driven evidence to make any further inferences in the means between the men’s and women’s prevention measure rates of this study.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/SexDistHistogram.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/SexDistHistogram.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>