<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-05-08T21:01:36-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">A Look into ‘Healthy Aging’ - Exploring older patients (65+) that are up to date with clinical preventative measures</title><subtitle>This site will be used for our final project, a blog about healthcare analytics. The main topic will be focusing on the trends of men and women's compliance with CDC preventative measure guidelines.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Results and Findings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/07/results.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Results and Findings" /><published>2022-05-07T08:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-07T08:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/07/results</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/07/results.html">&lt;p&gt;After exploring the data further, we drew a histogram to look at the distribution of gender in the original dataset. Below you will see an ‘overlaid histogram’ that is showing the men in the data set (in blue) and the women (in red). We can see from the histogram that the data is more or less normally distributed. There appears to be a left skew for the women, but it is not a drastic view by any means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;histogram-of-prevention-rates-men-blue-and-women-red&quot;&gt;Histogram of Prevention Rates: Men (Blue) and Women (Red)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/SexDistHistogram.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Above is an overlaid histogram of the male and female prevention rates and a box-and-whisker plot. The purpose of creating the histogram is to see if our data were normally distributed across both sexes, which seems to be the case with a slight skew to the left. The hypothesis we decided to work from was to determine if there are any variances in the preventative measures succeession rates between males and females. Therefore, we selected the student t-test as our measurement tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon inspecting the graph, we notice that the men seemed to have an overall higher success rate in satisfying the CDC’s preventative measures guidelines than the women. This observation ran contrary to Ben’s expectations as he predicted the contrary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hypothesis-testing&quot;&gt;Hypothesis Testing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the dataset we can see that there is normal distribution for both genders in respect to the success rate of CDC preventative measure compliance. However, we wanted to take this a step further and understand if there were any variances in the preventative measure of success rates across genders. Our method of choice for measurement was the student t-test. The conditions of our dataset satisfied the requirements of a student t-test such as an even distribution of the two samples (equal numbers of men and women participants) and that the factor of sex is an independent variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that the null hypothesis we tested against, in the context of measuring variance in the success rate of CDC preventative measures compliance across sexes, was there is no variance between the mean success rates of men and women. The alternative hypothesis then would mean that there is a variance or difference between the mean success rates of men and women for CDC preventative measure compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hypothesis-test&quot;&gt;Hypothesis Test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the analysis section, we are testing whether or not the null hypothesis is valid. Please see below for the null hypothesis testing and the methodology we followed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Null Hypothesis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Men and Women’s mean rate of preventative measures success are identical.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alternative Hypothesis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Men and Women’s mean rate of preventative measures success are different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We read our data into a Pandas dataframe in our local Python environment and then proceeded to separate the data into male and female dataframe objects. We then calculated the mean values of the preventative measures percentage columns for both the male and female dataframes. Then we aggregated the means by state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before sending the data through scipy.stats’s t-test_ind function, we needed to preprocess the data as the function could not handle numbers with such large precision values. To work around this issue, we passed the data through scipy.special’s logsumexp function, which returns the log sum of the exponent of the input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/finalResults.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;New Image&quot; style=&quot;width:1000px;height:180px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above is a screenshot of our student t-test. As the p-value is less than 0.05, we can safely reject the null hypothesis, meaning that there is evidence that a variance in means between the men’s rate and women’s rate of CDC prevention compliance exists. In other words, the probability that the t-statistic (5.022%) actually existing within a 95% confidence interval of our data was so insignificant, that we cannot assume the null hypothesis to be the truth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">After exploring the data further, we drew a histogram to look at the distribution of gender in the original dataset. Below you will see an ‘overlaid histogram’ that is showing the men in the data set (in blue) and the women (in red). We can see from the histogram that the data is more or less normally distributed. There appears to be a left skew for the women, but it is not a drastic view by any means.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/SexDistHistogram.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/SexDistHistogram.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Technologies Implemented</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/06/technologies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technologies Implemented" /><published>2022-05-06T10:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-06T10:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/06/technologies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/06/technologies.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;hardware-requirements&quot;&gt;Hardware Requirements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We utilized laptops that run both Windows and macOS operating systems. To replicate this analysis, we recommend your machine has at least 16GB of Random Access Memory (RAM).
&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/applelog.jpeg&quot; style=&quot;width:200px;height:200px&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/windowsIcon.png&quot; style=&quot;width:200px;height:200px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;software-requirements&quot;&gt;Software Requirements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our blog site deployment and source control, we used GitHub Pages and GitHub respectively. We built the site using Jekyll.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/jekyll_icon.png&quot; style=&quot;width:650px;height:280px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Breakdown of the Technical requirements for this project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Code Environment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:
We utilized the Visual Studio Code IDE as well as its Jupyter Notebook plugin to develop the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Pre-Processing and Cleaning&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: 
We extracted the raw data from the PLACES website and removed extraneous columns while retaining the columns that we needed to analyze. 
The data reading and manipulations were handled by the Pandas library, namely the unique dataframe object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:
The Hypothesis testing was conducted using the Scipy library in Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Visualizations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:
The Visualizations were created using the Plotly library and the geospatial visual used Plotly, Shapely, and GeoPandas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/pythonlogo.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Hardware Requirements We utilized laptops that run both Windows and macOS operating systems. To replicate this analysis, we recommend your machine has at least 16GB of Random Access Memory (RAM). Software Requirements For our blog site deployment and source control, we used GitHub Pages and GitHub respectively. We built the site using Jekyll.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Big Data in Healthcare</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/02/bigdataHealth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Big Data in Healthcare" /><published>2022-05-02T10:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-02T10:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/02/bigdataHealth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/05/02/bigdataHealth.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/statecounts.png&quot; /&gt;
This is a bar graph showing the prevalence of men and women aged 65 years and older who are up-to-date with the recommended core set of clinical preventive services. This project provides model-based small area estimates for 27 measures of chronic disease related to unhealthy behaviors (5), health outcomes (13), and use of preventive services (9). Data were provided by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), Division of Population Health, Epidemiology and Surveillance Branch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the small area model cannot detect effects due to local interventions, users are cautioned against using these estimates for program or policy evaluations. Data sources used to generate these measures include Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (BRFSS) data (2013, 2014), Census Bureau 2010 census population data, and American Community Survey (ACS) 2009-2013, 2010-2014 estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/PlacesUSA.png&quot; /&gt;
This map shows all locations where the PLACES surveys took place. The majority of the survey calls were made in the states of California, Texas, Florida, Illinois, and Michigan. The points colored in red on the map represent the states where the majority of survey calls were made whereas every other state’s survey locations are marked in blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is notable about this observation in regards to the survey is that the majority of the US population seems to be concentrated in certain environments. If the probability of most chronic illnesses, diseases and viruses affecting the target population can be traced to the environment, then a potential bias surrounding these five states and their environments’ characteristics may be affecting the PLACES survey efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">This is a bar graph showing the prevalence of men and women aged 65 years and older who are up-to-date with the recommended core set of clinical preventive services. This project provides model-based small area estimates for 27 measures of chronic disease related to unhealthy behaviors (5), health outcomes (13), and use of preventive services (9). Data were provided by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), Division of Population Health, Epidemiology and Surveillance Branch.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dataset Limitations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/29/dataBias.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dataset Limitations" /><published>2022-04-29T08:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-29T08:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/29/dataBias</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/29/dataBias.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;potential-bias&quot;&gt;Potential Bias&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While exploring initial questions for this project, we discovered that the data we had from PLACES was not comprehensive enough, which we suspect will lead to potential bias. We highly recommend gathering additional data and conducting ‘Logistic Regression’ to analyze how the preventative measures correspond to immunization rates. A further study incorporating these components would help uncover more patterns regarding prevenative care measures across the country which would be highly beneficial to the CDC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking into the very nature of the dataset, we can see where the bias might have originated, as participant data was collected over the phone. The default answer to each phone question could have been a “yes”, leading to a ‘false positive’ result in the preventative measure data. This reason alone may explain why the response rate or signal is relatively low (approximately 35% across all states and regions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some states such as California and Texas have staggeringly larger numbers of people participating per location, compared to low-participation rate states such as Alaska or North Dakota. While this trend should make logical sense if the motivation is to study as many people as possible, the consequence or potential source of bias manifests in the lack of representation of less populated areas of the country. To further emphasize this point, states like California and Texas that have higher populations and population densities than states such as Alaska or Wyoming far surpass the most populous cities in low population and low population density states. Hence, the lack of even population and population density distributions among states presents a potential for confirmation bias, which renders any subsequent analysis using this dataset, as found on the PLACES website, dubious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/biasimage.jpeg&quot; style=&quot;width=100px;height=220px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ca-and-tx-population-cross-tabulation&quot;&gt;CA and TX Population Cross Tabulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/bigCrosstab.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wy-and-ak-population-cross-tabulation&quot;&gt;WY and AK Population Cross Tabulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/smallCrosstab.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state of Wyoming has one city surveyed with a population size ranging between 50,000 to 100,000 people, whereas Texas and California have 18 and 55 cities surveyed respectively within the same population range.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Potential Bias While exploring initial questions for this project, we discovered that the data we had from PLACES was not comprehensive enough, which we suspect will lead to potential bias. We highly recommend gathering additional data and conducting ‘Logistic Regression’ to analyze how the preventative measures correspond to immunization rates. A further study incorporating these components would help uncover more patterns regarding prevenative care measures across the country which would be highly beneficial to the CDC.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Descriptive Statistics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/27/descriptiveAnalysis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Descriptive Statistics" /><published>2022-04-27T10:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-27T10:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/27/descriptiveAnalysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/27/descriptiveAnalysis.html">&lt;p&gt;For this project, we explored survey data taken from Americans aged 65+ in 500 cities across the United States. The dataset we explored had information about adherence to CDC preventive measures and guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The raw data that we explored was rather unorganized, and outliers, and had missing data. One of the biggest issues we faced was the inability to use one of the essential columns ‘GeoLocation’. We were not able to use this column until we decoupled the object and converted the string data into a floating-point data type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;jupyter-notebook-image&quot;&gt;Jupyter Notebook image&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/metadata.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also removed about 30 columns worth of data that were not relevant to our analysis. Below you will see the Metadata for the 13 columns that we were left with after completing data cleaning. The columns of the biggest interest are ‘DataValue’, ‘Short QuestionText’, while the columns ‘PouplationCount’, ‘CityName’, and ‘StateAbbr’ add value to our descriptive analysis as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ait580blog/assets/images/descriptiveStatistics.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking into the specifics of the data, we can see the standard deviation, mean, and maximum values from the descriptive statistics above.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">For this project, we explored survey data taken from Americans aged 65+ in 500 cities across the United States. The dataset we explored had information about adherence to CDC preventive measures and guidelines.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/metadata.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/metadata.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Curation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/25/dataCuration.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Curation" /><published>2022-04-25T09:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-25T09:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/25/dataCuration</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/25/dataCuration.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-curators&quot;&gt;Data Curators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As one of their goals entails disseminating information to the public, members of the CDC often conduct scientific experiments, collect data, host and conduct public-health seminars and place their results and data on their website. This centralization model makes finding specific information, research efforts and general inquiries easy to address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;places-motivation&quot;&gt;PLACES Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of PLACES was to provide information on a zip code-by-zip code basis, identify key health problems, develop localized plans moving forward, and differentiate the health threats affecting citizens living in various areas such as urban, rural or suburban areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-quality&quot;&gt;Data Quality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dataset we selected was nowhere near ready for analysis. The main focus of this dataset is targeting population groups in different geographic areas, but the data for the geolocations were nested inside of a data object in the form of strings. This made geospatial analysis impossible to conduct with our code as the dataset came downloaded, so there was plenty of data cleaning that had to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, most of the metadata on the CDC’s websites hardly explained any of the actual fields of the dataset we worked with. The methodology of the research seemed to explain more about the data rather than the dataset’s own documentation which was rather unsettling if the CDC is determined to inform the public about health matters. However, having Bethlehem’s expertise in healthcare made understanding the data easier, which made the analysis more straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did not encounter any security protocols or identity authentications to acquire this dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Data Curators As one of their goals entails disseminating information to the public, members of the CDC often conduct scientific experiments, collect data, host and conduct public-health seminars and place their results and data on their website. This centralization model makes finding specific information, research efforts and general inquiries easy to address.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Questions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/18/Questions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Questions" /><published>2022-04-18T09:26:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-18T09:26:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/18/Questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/18/Questions.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;questions&quot;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the project we contemplated to answer the following questions:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;1) What is the overall geographic distribution of the survey-respondents across the United States?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;2) What is the difference in the rates between male and female senior citizens’ adherance to CDC preventative measure guidelines?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;3) Which states have a higher rate of senior-compliance?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;4) Why are some participants not captured? What are some of the limits of this survey?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the scope of the project and limited time frame, some of the questions will be addressed in our ‘Limitations’ section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given our dataset, we chose to address differences in participation of the PLACES survey between the two sexes. There were other considerations for our research such as assessing geographical differences of the PLACES survey locations. The problem with that specific idea is the dataset doesn’t seem to include any rural or suburban areas despite one of the goals of the PLACES initative being able to differentiate the health problems across different environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparing the sexes seems to be the least problematic given our dataset as there is an even distribution of men and women. What would be neat to see are differences between the male and female prevention rates to see if there is any causal or behavioral explanation to inspect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Questions In the project we contemplated to answer the following questions: 1) What is the overall geographic distribution of the survey-respondents across the United States? 2) What is the difference in the rates between male and female senior citizens’ adherance to CDC preventative measure guidelines? 3) Which states have a higher rate of senior-compliance? 4) Why are some participants not captured? What are some of the limits of this survey?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/Whiteboard.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/assets/images/Whiteboard.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">References and Data Gathering</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/15/References.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="References and Data Gathering" /><published>2022-04-15T09:26:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-15T09:26:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/15/References</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/15/References.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Goldin, Ian. “The World before This Coronavirus and after Cannot Be the Same.” The Conversation, The Conversation, 27 Mar. 2020, https://theconversation.com/the-world-before-this-coronavirus-and-after-cannot-be-the-same-134905.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] “PLACES: Local Data for Better Health CDC.” Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 4 Apr. 2022, https://www.cdc.gov/places/index.html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] “500 Cities: Bar Graph of the Prevalence of Men and Women Aged 65 and Older Who Are up-to-Date with the Recommended Core Set of Clinical Preventive Services Chronic Disease and Health Promotion Data &amp;amp; Indicators.” Socrata, https://chronicdata.cdc.gov/500-Cities-Places/500-Cities-Bar-graph-of-the-prevalence-of-men-and-/3vvb-3n6b. Accessed 5 Apr. 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] “Mars vs. Venus: The Gender Gap in Health - Harvard Health Publishing - Harvard Health.” Harvard Health, 1 Jan. 2010, https://www.health.harvard.edu/newsletter_article/mars-vs-venus-the-gender-gap-in-health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] “Big Data in HealthCare and Patient Outcomes.” Online Public Health &amp;amp; Healthcare Administration Degrees, https://publichealth.tulane.edu/blog/big-data-in-healthcare/. Accessed 1 May 2022.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">References [1] Goldin, Ian. “The World before This Coronavirus and after Cannot Be the Same.” The Conversation, The Conversation, 27 Mar. 2020, https://theconversation.com/the-world-before-this-coronavirus-and-after-cannot-be-the-same-134905.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Terms Used</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/14/terms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Terms Used" /><published>2022-04-14T09:22:52-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-14T09:22:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/14/terms</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ait580blog/jekyll/update/2022/04/14/terms.html">&lt;p&gt;Below are some of the terms we have used in the project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLACES&lt;/strong&gt;: Population Level Analysis Community Estimates&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CDC&lt;/strong&gt;: Center for Disease Control&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHO&lt;/strong&gt;:  World Health Organization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regression Model&lt;/strong&gt;: ​​A regression model provides a function that describes the relationship between one or more independent variables and a response, dependent, or target variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Logistic Regression&lt;/strong&gt;:Logistic regression is a process of modeling the probability of a discrete outcome given an input variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dengue&lt;/strong&gt;: Dengue is a mosquito-borne viral disease that has rapidly spread to all regions of WHO in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ebola&lt;/strong&gt;: Ebola Virus Disease (EVD) is a rare and deadly disease in people and nonhuman primates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SARS&lt;/strong&gt;: Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) is a viral respiratory disease caused by a SARS-associated coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;H1N1&lt;/strong&gt;: The H1N1 flu, commonly known as swine flu, is primarily caused by the H1N1 strain of the flu (influenza) virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zika&lt;/strong&gt;: Zika virus disease is caused by a virus transmitted primarily by Aedes mosquitoes, which bite during the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pandas&lt;/strong&gt;: Pandas is a fast, powerful, flexible and easy to use open source data analysis and manipulation tool, built on top of the Python programming language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt;: Python is a high-level, interpreted, general-purpose programming language.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Below are some of the terms we have used in the project:</summary></entry></feed>